Guide to the Merle Hoffman Papers, circa 1944-2012 and undated, bulk 1961-2000 RL.00557
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Merle Hoffman papers
circa 1944-2012 and undated bulk 1961-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hoffman, Merle
RL.00557
100 Linear Feet
Abortion rights activist and the publisher of the feminist magazine ON THE ISSUES. The bulk of the collection consists of the records of Choices Women's Medical Center, a New York City women's health clinic and abortion clinic co-founded by Hoffman in 1971, and the organizational records for ON THE ISSUES, a feminist magazine owned by Choices and overseen by Hoffman. The remainder of the collection consists of Hoffman's personal papers, mostly related to her pro-choice activism. The collection also includes writings by or interviews with many activists, such as Aung San Suu Kyi, Charlotte Bunch, Phyllis Chesler, Andrea Dworkin, Kate Millett, Marge Piercy, and Elie Wiesel. The correspondence, administrative files, minutes, manuals, reports, surveys, research files, electronic records, clippings, flyers, brochures, newsletters, photographs, and audiovisual materials in the collection provide rich material for the study of the history of abortion, the pro-choice movement, women's health care, and the anti-abortion movement in the United States. The records of Choices Women's Medical Center are especially valuable for understanding the medical practice of abortion, as well as the political context of that practice. Other topics that can be explored through the materials include contraception, women's rights and feminism, and rape. The addition (04-041 and 04-062) (18,750 items, 30 linear feet; dated 1971-2003) consists primarily of administrative and financial files from Choices Women's Medical Center and predecessor clinics, including correspondence, financial reports, public relations and media files, board meeting files, policy and procedure manuals, subject files, insurance files, program files, grants files, legal files, and files related to ON THE ISSUES magazine. Also included are a small number of Hoffman's personal writings. This accession is unprocessed and closed to researchers. Addition (05-023) (5150 items, 12 lin. ft; dated 1978-2003) consists primarily of administrative and financial records from Choices Women's Medical Center, including correspondence, financial reports, public relations and media files. Also includes board meeting, subject, insurance, program, legal and grant files, as well as policy and procedure manuals; 33 videotapes, 84 slides, 54 photographs and contact sheets; 1 CD-ROM; printed materials; and promotional calendars. Accession is unprocessed and closed to researchers.
68275 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Also, the audiovisual materials in this collection are not immediately accessible because they require formatting for use copies before use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Merle Hoffman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2000.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1946 Mar. 6 Born, Philadelphia, Pa.
1964 Graduated, LaGuardia High School of Performing Arts
1971 With Dr. Martin Gold, founded Choices Women's Medical Center, New York City; President
1972 B.A., Queens College, New York City
1972-1975 Enrolled in doctoral program in social psychology, City University of New York
1976 First president of the National Association of Abortion Facilities (NAAF)
1979 Married to Martin Gold
1982 Founded On the Issues magazine
1985 Founded New York Pro-Choice Coalition
Merle Hoffman is an abortion rights activist and the publisher of the feminist magazine On The Issues. Hoffman has been active in many national and New York City pro-choice organizations, including the National Association of Abortion Facilities, the New York Pro-Choice Coalition, and the National Coalition of Abortion Providers.
Historical Note
Choices Women's Medical Center is a feminist women's health clinic and a major abortion provider in New York City. It was among the first outpatient abortion facilities in the United States. Originally operating under the name Flushing Women's Medical Center, the clinic was founded in 1971 as an ambulatory abortion provider for Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York (HIP). It gradually expanded into other areas of women's health and, during the 1990s, into women's mental health. By the mid-1990s, the clinic was serving over 50,000 patients per year, and Hoffman has described it as one of the largest women's health facilities in the U.S.
Collection Overview
The papers of Merle Hoffman span the years from about 1944 to 2001, with most of the papers dating between 1961 and 2001. The collection is arranged in the following series: Choices, On the Issues, Personal Files, Photographic Materials, and Audiovisual Materials. The bulk of the materials consist of the records of Choices Women's Medical Center, a New York City women's health clinic and abortion clinic co-founded by Hoffman in 1971, and the organizational records for On the Issues, a feminist magazine owned by Choices and overseen by Hoffman. The remainder of the collection consists of Hoffman's personal papers, mostly related to her pro-choice activism. The collection also includes writings by or interviews with many activists such as Aung San Suu Kyi, Charlotte Bunch, Phyllis Chesler, Andrea Dworkin, Kate Millett, Marge Piercy, and Elie Wiesel. The correspondence, administrative files, minutes, manuals, reports, surveys, research files, electronic records, clippings, flyers, brochures, newsletters, photographs, and audiovisual materials in the collection provide rich material for the study of the history of abortion, the pro-choice movement, women's health care, and the anti-abortion movement in the United States. The records of Choices Women's Medical Center are especially valuable for understanding the medical practice of abortion, as well as the political context of that practice. Other topics that can be explored through the materials include contraception, women's rights and feminism, and rape.
The political context of abortion is further documented throughout the rest of the collection. Hoffman's writings, speeches, and interviews on abortion illuminate the abortion debate in the media. At the same time, the internal dynamics of the pro-choice movement are documented in files on various New York and national pro-choice organizations. The collection includes some materials on the National Association of Abortion Facilities (NAAF), the National Abortion Federation (NAF), the National Coalition of Abortion Providers (NCAP), the National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL), and the National Organization for Women (NOW). Especially noteworthy are the detailed meeting minutes and other records for the New York Pro-Choice Coalition, an umbrella organization for New York City pro-choice organizations founded by Hoffman in the mid 1980s.
In addition to her pro-choice activities, Merle Hoffman has been a vocal proponent of patient self-empowerment; an active supporter of various political candidates in New York City; and a feminist activist. The collection reflects these interests to varying degrees. The records of On the Issues magazine are especially useful as a source of writings on a broad range of feminist and other issues.
The Choices Series documents the day-to-day operations of Choices Women's Medical Center, including the clinic's medical policies and procedures, its internal administration, and its relationship with patients and community organizations. The series is divided into the following subseries: Correspondence, Subject Files, Legal Papers, Personnel, Security, Staff Files, Marketing, Operations, and Electronic Format. Much of the series consists of files on administrative issues, dating primarily from the late 1980s to the late 1990s. A few records date from the clinic's early years in the 1970s. The files also document the clinic staff's rising concern about Operation Rescue, militant anti-abortion protests, and anti-abortion violence during the late 1980s and 1990s. At the same time, the Choices records suggest how the ideals of feminist health care and patient empowerment have translated into medical practice. The records primarily provide the perspective of health providers rather than patients; the collection does not include patient medical records. However, patient surveys and a limited amount of patient correspondence provide some evidence of patient experience at the clinic. There is substantial material on the Choices East Project, Hoffman's unsuccessful attempt to establish a women's health clinic in Moscow. Choices' treatment philosophy of patient self-empowerment and its identity as a woman-friendly health care provider are documented in the Outreach Subseries and the Marketing Subseries. Information on patient experiences and reactions to the clinic can be found primarily through patient surveys, patient satisfaction questionnaires, and statistical summaries of patient demographics, all found in the Subject Files, Marketing, and Electronic Format Subseries. Choices organizational charts and staff rosters are available for reference in the Research Room's inventory drawers; please contact Research Services.
On the Issues (1983-1999), a feminist magazine, was founded by Merle Hoffman and produced by Choices staff. The magazine covered a broad range of feminist issues and topics, including but not limited to abortion and other women's health issues. During the 1990s the magazine became increasingly professionalized, moved from annual to quarterly publication, and operated more independently of Choices. The documents in the On The Issues Series provide an extensive record of the magazine's production and distribution. They primarily date from the 1990s and are organized into the following subseries: Issues, Correspondence, Article Files, Editorial Files, Production and Distribution, Marketing, Staff Files, Administration, and Electronic Format. The series includes a nearly complete run of issues. Files include reader surveys; mailing lists; drafts and correspondence from contributors; editorials by Hoffman and other writers; and working files maintained by individual editors and production staff. Electronic files contain similar materials, and include graphics.
The Personal Files Series is arranged into the following subseries: Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, Subject Files, Politics and Activism, New York Pro-Choice Coalition, Calendars, Phone Messages, Clippings, General Personal Files, and Electronic Format. The materials extensively document Hoffman's work as a writer, public speaker, organizer, and activist for abortion rights and other feminist causes. Hoffman's personal publicity materials, including curriculum vitae and biographical sketches, can also be found in this series. There are also some records of Hoffman's childhood and personal life. The correspondence, found in both the Correspondence and Electronic Format Subseries, contains significant personal exchanges with feminists, friends, and colleagues that span many decades. Pro-choice organizations represented in the series include the New York Pro-Choice Coalition (NYPCC), the National Organization for Women (NOW), the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), and the National Association of Abortion Facilities (NAAF). The series also contains Hoffman's phone message books, calendars, and scrapbooks, including those related to her work at Choices and On the Issues. Electronic files contain a variety of correspondence, mailing lists, graphics, Choice and On the Issues documents mixed on the same disks, and a few writings. Overall, the series amply illustrates the porous nature of the boundary between Hoffman's personal activities and her work at Choices and On the Issues.
The Photographic Materials Series contains a variety of material related to Choices Women's Medical Center, On the Issues magazine, and Hoffman's personal activities. Especially notable are the numerous images of the Choices clinic facilities and procedures, and the detailed visual record of pro-choice rallies and other events involving Hoffman during the 1980s. Political figures pictured in this series include Bella Abzug, Hilary Clinton, Andrea Dworkin, Geraldine Ferraro, Flo (Florynce) Kennedy, Congressman John Lewis, and Gloria Steinem. Other photographs in the Personal Subseries include portraits of Hoffman and snapshots from a vacation at the feminist Camp Sister Spirit.
The bulk of the Audiovisual Materials Series consists of audio recordings on cassette tape of New York City radio talk shows featuring Merle Hoffman as an interview subject. Most interviews date from the 1970s or early 1980s. In some cases, these recordings feature Hoffman responding to listeners in call-in discussions of abortion, or conducting debates with anti-abortion representatives. Other audio recordings include interviews conducted for On the Issues stories and radio advertisements for Choices. Videotape recordings include several episodes of "On the Issues," Merle Hoffman's cable access television show, and some documentary material on Choices and its patients. Materials are not immediately accessible until use copies can be made upon request. Please consult with reference staff before coming to use the collection.
Finally, the Ephemera Series contains various memorabilia, including a box of Choices condoms, buttons, and banners with feminist and political slogans.
Later accessions (2004-0041, 2004-0062, 2005-0023, and 2012-0049) have been added to the end of the finding aid. Boxlists are included when known.
Related Material
For related materials, see the Phyllis Chesler Papers and the Kate Millett Papers. In addition, researchers may find the Takey Crist Papers, which document the activities and history of an abortion provider's clinic, to be particularly relevant. All of these collections are held by the Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Contraception -- United States; Pro-life movement -- United States; Feminism -- United States; Rape -- United States; Abortion -- Press coverage -- United States; Videocassettes; Machine-readable records; Audiocassettes; Women's health services -- New York (State); Women's health services -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Abortion services -- New York (State) -- New York; Abortion services -- New York (State); Abortion services -- United States; Abortion clinics -- United States; Women's health services -- United States; Women's health clinics -- United States; Women's health clinics -- New York (State) -- New York; Women's health clinics -- New York (State); Pro-choice movement -- New York (State); Pro-choice movement -- New York (State) -- New York; Women -- Health and hygiene -- United States; Abortion -- Political aspects; Abortion -- New York (State); Abortion -- United States; Women's rights -- United States; Pro-choice movement; Piercy, Marge; Wiesel, Elie, 1928-; Hoffman, Merle; Millett, Kate; Dworkin, Andrea; Chesler, Phyllis; Choices (Organization); Aung San Suu Kyi; Bunch, Charlotte, 1944-
- Choices Series, 1945-2000 and undated, bulk 1976-2000, 48 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains records documenting the policies, practices, and daily operations of the Choices Women's Medical Center, one of the first outpatient abortion clinics in the United States as well as a general women's health provider. Organized into the following subseries: Correspondence, Subject Files, Legal Papers, Personnel, Security, Staff Files, Marketing, Operations, and Electronic Format. Choices organizational charts and staff rosters are available for reference in the Research Room's inventory files; please contact Research Services.
  The Choices records primarily provide the perspective of health providers rather than patients. However, the series does includes some information on patient experience at the clinic; see especially the patient surveys and questionnaires in the Subject Files Subseries, and a small amount of patient correspondence in the Correspondence Subseries. In addition, the Marketing Files contain some information on the demographics of Choices patients. Staff involvement in the wider pro-choice movement and in other political causes, as well as defending against anti-abortion violence, is documented throughout the series; see especially the Subject Files, the Outreach Subseries, and the Security Subseries. Pro-choice organizations represented in the series include the National Abortion Federation and the National Coalition of Abortion Providers. See below for further description of each subseries.
  Related materials can be found in the Personal Series, the Photographic Materials Series, and the Audiovisual Series.
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1972-1999 and undated
    The Correspondence Subseries includes internal Choices memos and e-mails. The subseries is in alphabetical order. See the Personal Series for additional Choices correspondence.
    - Aisenberg, Karen (Executive Assistant), 1992 (Box CH1)
    - DeCerbo, David (attorney), 1989-1998 (Box CH1)
    - Farrell, Annette, 1993-1997 and undated (Box CH1)
    - Fee increase notifications, 1982 (Box CH1)
    - General correspondence, 1978-1999 and undated, 3 folders (Box CH1)
    - Hate mail, 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box CH1)
    - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, approval of Choices, 1972-1975 (Box CH1)
    - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, 1992-1997 (Box CH1)
    - Hoffman, Merle, 1991-1993 (Box CH1)
    - Hoffman, Merle, memos, 1991, 1 of 2 folders (Box CH1)
    - Hoffman, Merle, memos, 1991, 2 of 2 folders (Box CH2)
    - Hoffman, Merle - memos, 1992, 1995, 1997, 3 folders (Box CH2)
    - International Institute for the Advancement of Medicine, 1989-1990 (Box CH2)
    - Landlord complaint, 1995 (Box CH2)
    - Jamaica Hospital, 1994-1998 (Box CH2)
    - Kennedy, Kay, 1994-1995 (Box CH2)
    - Kessler, Martha (estate of Thomas Jay Mullin), 1994-1996 (Box CH2)
    - Lease and renovations, 1977-1978 (Box CH2)
    - Marketing and outreach, 1992-1994 (Box CH2)
    - Memos, 1995 (Box CH2)
    - New York City Bureau of Laboratories, 1977-1987 (Box CH2)
    - New York State Department of Health, 1978-1988 and undated (Box CH2)
    - New York State Department of Health notebook, 1989-1991, 3 folders (Box CH2)
    - New York State Department of Health notebook, 1992-1995, 6 folders (Box CH3)
    - New York State Department of Health notebook, procedures and policies, 1994-1995 (Box CH3)
    - Parke-Davis, 1993-1995 (Box CH3)
    - Patient complaints, 1994 and 1999 (Box CH3)
    - Patient thanks letters and fan mail, 1979-1995 (Box CH3)
    - Personnel policy, 1987-1989 (Box CH3)
    - Queens Long Island Medical Group negotiations, 1995-1996 and undated (Box CH3)
    - WellCare managed care network, 1994-1996 and undated, 2 folders (Box CH4)
  - Subject Files Subseries, 1977-2000 and undated
    One of the largest subseries. Includes informational materials on abortion and other health issues, research files from clinic studies and patient surveys, and records of the clinic's involvement in various projects and organizations. There is a significant amount of material on the Choices East (Moscow) project, Hoffman's unsuccessful attempt to establish a women's health clinic in Moscow in the early 1990s. A small portion of the Choices East files are in Russian.
    The subseries is subdivided into Abortion, Choices East, Patient Information, Research, and General Subject Files. Within each section, files are organized alphabetically. The Abortion files also document staff involvement in the National Coalition of Abortion Providers, the National Abortion Federation, and other pro-choice organizations. See the Oversize Material for additional Research files.
    - Abortion, 1977-2000 and undated
      - Abortion Alternative Hotline stamps, mounted for printing, undated (Box CH4)
      - Abortion Center Survival - A Partial Guide, 1984 (Box CH4)
      - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) and Rust v. Sullivan, 1991 (Box CH4)
      - Clippings, 1982-2000 and undated (Box CH4)
      - Clippings and newsletters, 1979, 1989-1997 and undated (Box CH4)
      - Counselor training - Abortion values exercises, 1983-1994 and undated (Box CH4)
      - "Legal Abortion in the United States" article, 1977 (Box CH4)
      - National Abortion Federation, 1989-1997, 2 folders (Box CH4)
      - National Abortion Federation - Warren Hern dispute, 1995-1997 (Box CH4)
      - National Coalition of Abortion Providers (NCAP), 1994-1997, 2 folders (Box CH5)
      - NCAP conference, 1996 (Box CH5)
      - NCAP - Open House project, 1996 (Box CH5)
      - NCAP - "Ron Fitzsimmons debacle," 1997 (Box CH5)
      - National Pro-Choice Directory, 1997 (Box CH5)
      - Non-surgical abortion information, 1994 (Box CH5)
      - Non-surgical abortion information and procedures, 1990-1997 and undated (Box CH5)
      - Opinion poll reports, 1982 (Box CH5)
      - Partial birth abortion - anti-abortion publications, 1997 and undated (Box CH5)
      - Pro-Choice Public Education Project, opinion poll results, 1997 (Box CH5)
      - Report on young women's attitudes towards pro-choice, 1997 (Box CH5)
      - Second trimester - available providers, 1979-1982 and undated (Box CH5)
      - Statistics, New York, 1991-1994 (Box CH5)
    - Choices East (Moscow), 1989-1997
      - American Medical Exchange's Russia Project, 1994 (Box CH5)
      - Birth control in Russia - clippings, 1992-1994 (Box CH5)
      - Clippings, 1992-1994 (Box CH5)
      - Correspondence, 1992-1997 (Box CH6)
      - Grants and foundations, 1994, 2 folders (Box CH6)
      - Lomunova, Margarita, article, 1992-1993 (Box CH6)
      - Lowey, Congresswoman Nita, 1994 (Box CH6)
      - Meetings with Marie Stopes International and PROFIT, 1994 (Box CH6)
      - Perlo, Dr. Mark, 1994 (Box CH6)
      - Planned Parenthood's Russia project, 1992-1993 (Box CH6)
      - Proposal (1989), 1989-1992 (Box CH6)
      - Proposal, 1992 (Box CH6)
      - Publicity consultants, 1993-1994 (Box CH6)
      - Resumes and job application letters, 1992-1995 (Box CH6)
      - Visit to Moscow (1992 Oct.)
        - Complete press report, 1992-1993 (Box CH6)
        - Planning, 1992 (Box CH6)
        - Presentation on clinic procedures, 1992 (Box CH6)
        - Press conference, 1992 (Box CH6)
      - Visit to Moscow (1992 Oct.) (Box CH7)
        - Publicity, 1992-1994 (Box CH7)
        - Supplies and sponsors, 1989-1994 (Box CH7)
      - Visit to Moscow (1994 Jan./Feb.)
        - Media contacts, 1994 (Box CH7)
        - Supplies and sponsors, 1994 (Box CH7)
      - Visit to Moscow (1994 Jun.)
        - Moscow press, 1994 (Box CH7)
        - Bernie Rome and Maya Ermalova, 1994 (Box CH7)
        - Supplies and sponsors, 1994 (Box CH7)
      - Wildfeir, Nancy (marketing), 1993-1994 (Box CH7)
      - Zhenshchina: Zemlya/ Women and Earth and related paperwork, 1993 (Box CH7)
      - Wyeth-Ayers (birth control supplies), 1992-1993 (Box CH7)
    - Patient Information, 1970s-1998 and undated
      - "Birth control book. Original," 1970s (Box CH7)
      - Birth control pamphlet, undated (Box CH7)
      - Clinic signs, undated (Box CH7)
      - For male partners of abortion patients, undated (Box CH7)
      - Handouts collection, 1995 and undated (Box CH7)
      - Insurance accepted and Mental Health Center fees, 1990s (Box CH8)